Have you ever wondered
if there are more natural ways
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we look at the
powerful properties of NAD+.
And no, it’s not just another
streaming platform…
NAD+ is an essential cofactor
for hundreds of enzymes,
with a potential role to
play in the aging process.
Our understanding of nicotinamide
adenine dinucleotide (NAD+)
arose from humble beginnings as a factor
noted to enhance yeast fermentation
in a 1906 paper unassumingly entitled
“The Alcoholic Ferment of Yeast-Juice.”
Little did they know that
waves of NAD-related discoveries
would go on to yield a
total of four Nobel Prizes.
NAD+ is now known as an essential
molecule for all living organisms,
required for the function
of about 500 enzymes,
including, notably, the extraction
of metabolic energy from food.
The 21st century has produced yet
another scientific renaissance for NAD+
with the realization that it was
critical for the activity of sirtuins,
the “guardians of mammalian healthspan”
I detail in my book, How Not to Age.
NAD+ is one of the most abundant
molecules in our body.
Once considered relatively stable,
it’s now known to be in a constant state
of synthesis, recycling, and breakdown.
The entire pool of NAD+
in some of our tissues
is turned over
several times a day.
To maintain cellular vitality
in the face of this turnover,
an adequate supply
of NAD+ precursors
and sufficiently high enzyme activity
synthesizing NAD+ are critical.
The importance of NAD+ is exemplified
by the devastating consequences
of a deficiency of NAD+ precursors
like niacin (vitamin B3).
The deficiency syndrome,
called pellagra,
is characterized by the 4 D’s:
dermatitis, dementia, diarrhea,
and, eventually, death.
Thankfully, since life as we know
it couldn’t exist without it,
NAD+ and its precursors are
found in everything we eat—
plant, animal, or fungi—
but we need to know
how to get at them.
The niacin in corn, for instance,
is tightly bound up,
but it can be released by pre-
soaking in alkaline lime-water.
Maize was exported
from Latin America
to become a dietary staple
without the requisite knowledge
about traditional processing
techniques, though,
and an epidemic
of pellagra ensued.
An estimated 100,000 Americans
died from pellagra
in the first few decades
of the 20th century
before bread started to be
fortified with niacin in 1938.
The pitch for NAD+ boosting as an
anti-aging strategy goes as follows:
all species,
including humans,
naturally experience a decline
in NAD+ levels over time,
and this decline is, in fact,
one of the major
reasons organisms age.
By restoring youthful levels,
the argument goes,
these age-related disorders can
be delayed or even reversed.
Two leaders in the field,
one from Harvard and the other MIT,
have said, respectively,
that NAD+ boosters may
“hold the promise of increasing
the body’s resilience,
not just to one disease,
but to many,
thereby extending healthy
human lifespan,”
and that sirtuin activation
by NAD+ repletion
“may be the most actionable item
to emerge from aging research.”
Of course, they have
both been involved
in multimillion-dollar dietary
supplement companies.
The first premise, that NAD+
levels decline with age,
has been called into question.
For example,
this 2022 review
“Age-Dependent Decline of NAD+—
Universal Truth or Confounded Consensus?”
concluded that, despite
systemic claims to the contrary,
the evidence supporting
the premise is very limited.
Indeed, the most
comprehensive study to date
found significant changes
in NAD+ levels
in less than half of the tested
tissues in old versus young mice.
The human data are
similarly inconsistent.
NAD+ boosting supplement
shills make claims like
“By middle age,
our NAD+ levels
have plummeted to half
that of our youth,”
but the cited source only shows a
drop (in brain levels) of about 13%
between about
the ages 20 to 60.
A similar study estimated about
an 18% drop from age 25 to 70,
both broadly consistent with a
14% drop in spinal tap fluid samples
taken from those over
age 45 (average age 71),
compared to those under
age 45 (average age 34).
It’s unclear if such modest differences
would have any consequences,
and a more recent study found
no significant differences at all
in brain nor muscle levels between
a young group (average age 21)
and an older group
(average age 69).
A study of skin samples found a greater
than 50% drop in young adults
compared to the skin of newborns,
and a further drop of about 60%
from young adults to middle age.
However, there did not seem to be
a further decline from middle to old age.
There was a small study that found
the NAD+ levels in the liver samples
of six older individuals
(average age 66)
was about 30% lower than that of
six younger individuals (average age 39).
NAD+ levels also may
be lower in macrophage
white blood cells
in older individuals,
but in the blood more generally,
half the studies showed
a decline with age,
and the other half didn’t.
By far the largest study
(enrolling 10 times more people
than the other studies combined)
found a slight drop in NAD+
in the aging bloodstreams
of men but no drop in women.
The bottom line is that,
given the conflicting results from the
remarkably few studies on the subject,
it’s misleading to say NAD+
universally decreases with age.
Regardless, the proof
is in the pudding.
What about the second premise
that boosting levels late in life
can improve health and longevity?
We’ll address that question, next.
The effects of NAD+ boosters
on aged rodents
have been described
in the medical literature
as “profound,” “dramatic”…
“remarkable….”
Treated mice had increased
physical activity, improved vision,
and strengthened bones while
delaying or preventing muscle loss,
hearing loss, cognitive decline,
and ovarian aging.
Benefits to nearly every organ
system have been documented,
including improved artery function,
brain function,
heart function,
immune function,
kidney function, liver function,
and muscle function.
For example, a single week of an
NAD+ booster was sufficient
to restore key markers of muscle
health in a 22-month-old mouse
to levels similar to that
of a 6-month-old mouse.
That’s roughly the equivalent
of reverting the muscle health
of a 70-year-old person back
to when they were just 20.
NAD+ boosters can also extend
the lifespans of animals,
presumed to be due to the elevation
of sirtuin activity dependent on NAD+.
This longevity effect
was first demonstrated
more than 20 years
ago in yeast cells.
An overexpression of the genes
involved in NAD+ synthesis
extended replicative lifespans
by as much as 60%.
In the microscopic
worm C. elegans,
NAD+-boosting compounds
have been shown
to extend lifespans
by up to 16%.
In mice, one NAD+ booster
was able to extend lifespan
by a more modest 5%,
but this was accomplished even when
supplementation was started late in life,
which is unusual for
longevity treatments.
No wonder people are excited about
all manner of NAD+ boosting supplements.
The big question is do any of
these healthspan or lifespan effects
translate to benefiting humans?
There are four major NAD+ boosting
supplements on the market these days:
nicotinic acid (NA),
also known as niacin,
nicotinamide (NAM),
also known as niacinamide,
nicotinamide riboside (NR),
and nicotinamide
mononucleotide (NMN).
NAD+ can also be given directly,
as well as its hydrogenated form NADH.
There are also hydrogenated
forms of NMN and NR,
also known as
dihydronicotinamide riboside.
So, there is quite
the alphabet soup:
NA, NAM, NMN, NR, NAD,
NADH, NMNH, and NRH.
The body can also make
NAD+ “from scratch”
from the amino
acid tryptophan.
Given the critical
nature of NAD+,
it is perhaps unsurprising that the
body has so many different pathways
utilizing a panoply
of precursors.
Converting tryptophan to
NAD+ requires eight steps,
whereas NA, NAM, and NR can be turned
into NAD+ in only two or three steps.
NMN is a direct
precursor of NAD+,
but when NMN or NR is taken orally,
it appears to just turn into NA or NAM,
via rapid degradation
in the bloodstream
or active conversion in the liver.
So, why take the more
expensive NMN or NR
if it’s just going to end
up as NA or NAM?
Bought in bulk, NA or NAM
would just cost pennies a day
versus more like a dollar
a day for NR or NMN.
That would add up to hundreds
of dollars a year for NR or NMN
compared to closer to only five bucks
for a whole year’s worth of NA or NAM.
But cost aside, what are the risks
and benefits of all these NAD boosters?
That’s exactly what I’ll cover, next.
The name nicotinic acid was
changed to niacin in the 1940s
to avoid any confusion
with nicotine.
Either name has to be better
than the original moniker, though:
vitamin PP
(for pellagra preventing).
In the 1950s, NA became the world’s
first cholesterol-lowering drug.
This led to more than 20 trials involving
tens of thousands of individuals
taking high doses of
NA for up to six years,
resulting in by far the most
robust safety data we have
on any of the NAD+ precursors.
The most striking benefit was found
in the Coronary Drug Project,
a trial carried out in the pre-statin
drug era of the 1960s and 70s.
The 15-year follow-up found that
those who had been randomized
to years of high-dose NA ended up
with a 6.2% drop in absolute mortality
(52% had died in the NA group
versus 58% in the placebo group).
This sparked major clinical trials that,
sadly, failed so spectacularly
that one was even
stopped prematurely.
All in all, a Cochrane meta-
analysis concluded that
“no evidence of benefits from
niacin therapy” was found.
One possible explanation
for the contrasting results
is that the early promising trials
used immediate release niacin,
while the newer failed trials
used slow release formulations
(also known as extended
or sustained release).
At high doses, regular niacin commonly
causes an intense flushing redness
and prickly heat sensation similar
to a menopausal hot flash.
A slow release version was developed
to reduce this flushing reaction,
catapulting it into a billion-
dollar blockbuster drug,
but it simply doesn’t work as
well to lower cholesterol.
The major clinical trial failures led
to the withdrawal of the drug in Europe
and the removal from
U.S. clinical guidelines
for cardiovascular
disease prevention.
There still may be a role
for niacin preparations
in the treatment
of heart disease
among patients who cannot
tolerate statin drugs,
but what about use for the
general public as an NAD+ booster?
There is a series of
rare genetic defects
that can lead to a condition
called mitochondrial myopathy
that’s characterized by low NAD+
levels in the blood and muscles.
In 2020, researchers demonstrated
that these levels could be repleted
with 750 to 1,000 mg
a day of NA,
which led to a significant
improvement in muscle strength.
This was the first and only study to show
improvements in muscle NAD+ levels
and performance with
any sort of NAD+ booster.
In a control group of individuals
without the genetic defect,
blood levels of NAD+
were raised by NA,
but not muscle levels,
suggesting that NAD+ levels are
already “topped off” in normal muscles.
As you’ll see, this is a recurring
theme among NAD+ boosters.
We know that large doses of NA
can boost NAD+ levels in human blood,
but a corresponding increase in sirtuin
activity has yet to be demonstrated.
Why not give it a try?
Because of the side effects unearthed
in the cholesterol-lowering trials.
NA raises blood sugars and may increase
your risk of developing diabetes.
Based on studies of tens of thousands
of people on high-dose NA
who were followed for years,
one would expect that 1 in 43
people taking NA for five years
would develop diabetes who
otherwise wouldn’t have.
It’s unclear if this risk is only limited
to slow release formulations.
The safety buffer, the ratio between
the tolerable upper limit and the RDA,
is the lowest for NA compared to
half a dozen other common vitamins.
However, the upper limit is just
based on the flushing reaction,
which although uncomfortable,
is considered harmless
and tends to dissipate over time.
Long-term use can have other
adverse consequences, though,
including stomach ulcers,
vomiting, abdominal pain,
diarrhea, and jaundice,
a sign of liver toxicity,
which is worse with
slow-release formulations.
There is also a theoretical concern
that excessive NA intake
may contribute to the development
of Parkinson’s disease.
Due to the unpleasant flushing and
risk of more serious side effects,
interest has moved towards
other NAD+ enhancers.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
All proceeds from book
sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.